Hartford National Corporation Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Hartford National Corporation Records.
undated, 1792-1995.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Hartford National Corporation.
180 linear feet.
MSS19980300
In 1969, the Hartford National Bank and Trust Company became the first completely owned subsidiary bank of the newly established Hartford National Corporation. After this merger, the HNC had assets totaled over $1.1 billion. The purchase of Connecticut National Bank would almost double the number of banks under its management and increase its assets drastically. The HNC merged with Shawmut National Corporation. Hartford remained one of the two dual headquarters for the corporation until its eventual merger with Fleet Bank in 1995.
History
Hartford National Corporation (1792-1988)
In 1969, the Hartford National Bank and Trust Company became the first completely owned subsidiary bank of the newly established Hartford National Corporation (HNC). After this merger, the HNC could boast assets totaling over $1.1 billion. Soon, the HNC expressed interest in purchasing the Connecticut National Bank (CNB), a merger that would almost double the number of banks under its management and increase its assets from $2.8 billion to over $4 billion.
In December 1981, shareholders from each bank voted in favor of the merger and in 1982 the merger took place. Now among the largest banking interests in southern New England, the HNC began looking for markets north of Connecticut. Changing interstate regulation laws allowed for a merger with Shawmut National Corporation, a Boston-based “Super-Regional” banking conglomerate, in 1988. Now amongst the largest twenty five banking concerns in the nation, the Shawmut National Corporation enjoyed assets totaling over $26 billion. Hartford, CT remained one of the two dual headquarters for the corporation until its eventual merger with Fleet Bank (now Bank of America) in 1995.
Note: For a detailed history of the Hartford National Corporation from 1792-1976, see the history provided in the introduction of the Hartford National Bank and Trust Company finding aid.
Connecticut National Bank
The Bridgeport Bank was founded by a small group of prominent Connecticut men on 20 November 1806. The citizens of the young borough of Bridgeport recognized that in order to facilitate their growing trade with the West Indies and Europe, they needed the stability of currency and financial assistance that could only be provided by a local bank. On 3 February 1807, the Board of Directors selected Isaac Bronson to fill the office of bank president. This wealthy and influential citizen lent his reputation to the bank and insured its survival when the British blockade all but suspended trade along the Atlantic seaboard during the War of 1812.
The Bridgeport Bank helped guide the borough, which became a city in 1836, from its early days as a center of trade through its emergence as a manufacturing center in the ante-bellum years. This period of the bank's history was marked by several financial panics resulting from over speculation. Yet when as a result of these recessions numerous Connecticut banks were forced to liquidate, the prudence and experience possessed by presidents such as Sylvanious Sterling (1837-1848) and Sherman Hartwell (1849-1869) insured the Bridgeport Bank joined the recently created National Banking System and became the Bridgeport National Bank.
A dramatic rise in manufacturing occurred in the Bridgeport area after the Civil War. During the twenty years between 1886-1906, the bank's deposits mushroomed from $60,000 to just over $1,000,000. This remarkable success fueled a series of mergers between the Bridgeport National Bank and its local rivals. In 1909, the bank merged with the First National Bank to become the First Bridgeport National Bank. Twelve years later after a merger with the Connecticut National Bank, the bank changed its name to the First National Bank of Bridgeport. Afterwards the bank developed trust and personal savings account services and in 1929 changed its name to the First National Bank and Trust Company of Bridgeport.
In 1933, the First National Bank and Trust Company of Bridgeport opened a branch office in Newfield after its merger with the Newfield Bank and Trust Company. No other Connecticut bank had opened a branch office since 1865, but soon most banks were following the First National Bank's initiative. More and more bank patrons were moving from city centers to reside in their surrounding suburbs. Banks could no longer rely solely on one downtown office to conduct business.
The First National Bank and Trust Company changed its name to the Connecticut National Bank in 1955 shortly after its merger with the Westport First National Bank. In that year, the Connecticut National Bank could boast deposits of over $100 million. Shortly before its controversial merger with the Hartford National Corporation, the Connecticut National Bank was worth over $700 million, making it one of the largest banking operations in the state.
After its merger with the HNC in 1982, the name of the Connecticut National Bank replaced that of the Hartford National Bank and Trust Company in every one of the 115 branches owned by the HNC. This situation changed when the HNC was purchased by the Boston-based Shawmut National Corporation in 1988.
Scope and Content
Much of the material in this collection complements and fills in gaps in the records of the Hartford National Bank and Trust Company (HNB&T) also located in Archives & Special Collections. Records dating from 1792-1976 should be used in conjunction with its materials and finding aid. Records dating from 1977-1995 document the bank's consolidation with the Hartford National Corporation and its subsequent merger with the Shawmut National Corporation in 1988. The Hartford National Corporation (HNC) collection also documents its merger with the Connecticut National Bank (CNB) in 1982. As a result of this merger, the HNC collection possesses over 80 linear feet of records produced by that organization.
Because of the important roles played by the HNC and the CNB in Connecticut's banking history, the records of both banks have been classified as separate series even though the CNB was one of the HNC's many merger banks. All records produced by other banks that eventually merged with either the HNC or the CNB constitute the third series of this collection. Series I and II are divided chronologically into five subseries that represent the numerous titles assumed by each bank since its establishment. Series III consists of two alphabetically arranged series that list banks absorbed by the HNC and the CNB, as well as several unidentified records and items.
Arrangement
Series I: Hartford National Corporation
A. Hartford National Bank (1792-1915)
B. Hartford-Aetna National Bank (1915-1927)
C. Hartford National Bank And Trust Company (1927-1969)
D. Hartford National Corporation (1969-1988)
E. Shawmut National Corporation (1892-1995)
Series Ii: Connecticut National Bank
A. Bridgeport National Bank (1806-1908)
B. First Bridgeport National Bank (1909-1921)
C. First National Bank Of Bridgeport (1921-29)
D. First National Bank And Trust Company Of Bridgeport (1929-1955)
E. Connecticut National Bank (1955-1982)
Series III: Merger Banks
A. Hartford National Corporation (1792-1988)
B. Connecticut National Bank (1806-1982)
Each subseries in Series I and II is divided into several section that delineate Records sharing common functions. Most of these subject headings are also used in the Hartford National Bank and Trust Company collection. These sections are: Financial Records, Corporate Records, Customer Records, Loan Records, Reports, Statements, and Condensed Statements of Condition, Reports on Examination, Advertisements and Promotional Publications, Currency, and Memorabilia.
Section 1: Financial Records, consists of records that document routine accounting and bookkeeping transactions. Such information is normally recorded in day books, fiscal ledgers, account books, income tax records, and cash books.
Section 2: Corporate Records, includes most materials relating to bank ownership and management. These records include charters, articles of association, by-laws, minute books, directors' records, capital stock records, stockholder records, annual reports, merger and consolidation proceedings, stock transfer records, agreements and contracts, insurance policies, miscellaneous subject files, and deeds.
Section 3: Customer Records, primarily consists of correspondence, but may also include checks, checkbooks, or deposit books.
Section 4: Loan Records, includes all documents related to loan transactions such as appraisals of loans, resumes covering loans and related correspondence.
Section 5: Reports, Statements, and Condensed Statements of Conditions, is composed of annual summaries of a bank's resources and liabilities. Resources are cross referenced with liabilities in order to insure that a bank possesses sufficient funds for its various commitments.
Section 6: Reports on Examination, consists of reports produced by professional bank examiners and accountants. A bank employs the services of these outside firms in order to possess clear and concise accounts of their financial transactions. These examinations are then normally used for tax and audit purposes.
Subseries 7: Advertisements and Promotional Publications, includes anniversary materials, newspaper articles, photographs, scrapbooks, published and unpublished works on banks and banking, and related subject files. These records document the important role played by banks in their communities and the image they hoped to portray to their patrons.
Section 8: Currency, consists of printed legal and counterfeit bank notes and currency plates.
Section 9: Memorabilia, includes items such as banks seals, paper weights, coin banks, and plaques.
Both Subseries in Series III contain the records of banks that eventually merged with either the HNC or the CNB. Although these banks also have possessed different names since their initial establishment, only the name that appears most often in the collection's records has been used. Unidentified records and items are located at the end of the second series.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut business records. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
Hartford National Bank and Trust Company—History.; Connecticut National Bank Bridgeport—History.
Subjects:
Banks and banking—Connecticut.; Corporations—Connecticut.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Books.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.
Occupations:
Financial institution.
Restrictions on Access
Materials containing personnally identifiable information regarding customers of the institution may be restricted. Please contact the curator for details.
Acquisition Information
The records of the Hartford National Corporation were donated along with the Hartford National Bank and Trust Company Records to Archives & Special Collections by the Shawmut Corporation in November 1995 at the time of its merger with Fleet Bank (now Bank of America). Later in May 1996, Archives & Special Collections received a smaller shipment of records from Fleet Bank that were integrated with those received during the previous year.
Detailed Description
- Series I:Hartford National Corporation, undated, 1792-1995)
  - Subseries A: Hartford (National) Bank, 1792-1915
    - Financial Records
      - Day Book, 1792-1793 (Box 1)
      - Original Subscriptions, 1793-1892
      - Register of discounts, 1795-1797
      - Ledger: discounts and deposits, 1792-1798 (Volume Vol. 1)
    - Corporate Records
      - Stock ledger, 1909-1926 (Volume Vol. 2)
      - Stock transfer book, 1843-1860 (Box 2)
      - Minute book: “Chronological List of Notes”, 1792-1932
      - Deeds, 1830-1910 (Box 3)
      - Quit Claims, 1895-1897
    - Customer Records
      - Correspondence, 1876-1914
    - Loan Records, undated
    - Advertisements and Promotional Publications, undated
      - Photographs of a new building, 1910
    - Currency
      - Counterfeit, 1852-1862
      - Legal, 1832-1862
    - Reports of Condition, 1897-1915 (Box 4)
  - Subseries B: Hartford-Aetna National Bank, 1915-1927
    - Financial Records
      - Examinations of resources and liabilities, 1926 (Box 5)
      - Tax returns, 1919-1920
    - Corporate Records
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1923-1927
      - Stock certificates, 1917-1926 (Box 6-8)
    - Customer Records
      - Correspondence, 1915-1927 (Box 9)
    - Reports on Examination, 1924 (Box 10)
  - Subseries C: Hartford National Bank and Trust Company, 1927-1969
    - Financial Records
      - General ledger, 1970-1972 (Box 11)
      - Records of bad debt, 1931-1948
      - Profit and loss records, 1868-1933
      - Ledger, 1921-1949
      - Ledger, 1934-1941
      - Ledger, 1941-1944
      - Income tax, 1929-1935 (Box 12)
      - Wages and hours, 1940-1948
      - Bills discounted, 1946-1949 (Volume Vol. 3)
      - Profit and loss statements, 1948-1949 (Volume Vol. 4)
      - General journal, 1949 (Volume Vol. 5)
      - Unsecured note register, 1961 (Volume Vol. 6)
      - Unsecured note register, 1962-1963 (Volume Vol. 7)
      - Secured note register, 1962 (Volume Vol. 8)
      - Secured note register, 1963 (Volume Vol. 9)
    - Corporate Records
      - Auditing Committee minutes, 1947-1954 (Box 13)
      - Employee pensions accounts, 1976 (Box 14)
      - Annual Reports, 1940-1968 (Box 15)
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1934-1968 (Box 16)
      - Employee pension trusts, 1974 (Box 17)
      - Subject files, 1923-1955 (Box 18)
      - Advisory board minutes, 1957-1967 (Box 19)
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1959-1967
      - Business correspondence, 1927-1949 (Box 20)
      - Construction bids and estimates, 1927-1928 (Box 21)
      - Building contracts, 1927-1928
      - List of stockholders, 1927
      - Mergers and consolidations, 1933-1958 (Box 22)
    - Customer Records
      - Correspondence, 1929-1960
      - Social security, 1937-1947
    - Loan Records
      - Appraisal of loans, 1934 (Box 23)
    - Reports of Condition, 1927-1939 (Box 24)
    - Reports of Condition, 1940-1952 (Box 25)
    - Reports of Condition, 1958-1960 (Box 26)
    - Condensed Reports of Condition, 1927-1953 (Box 27)
    - Condensed Statements of Condition, 1924-1963 (Box 28)
    - Reports on Examination, 1927
    - Reports on Examination, 1928-1938 (Box 29-31)
    - Advertisements and Promotional Publications
      - Ceremonial Photographs of new building, 1962-1968 (Box 32)
      - Subject files, 1958-1968 (Box 33)
      - “Hartnatopics”, 1944-1945
      - 165th Anniversary announcement, 1957
      - 175th Anniversary announcement, 1967
      - First National City Bank monthly letter, 1958-1959
      - Henry Turnbull Holt biography, undated
      - Slides of new building, 1962-1968 (Box 34)
      - Presidents of HNB&T Men's and Girl's Clubs, undated
      - “Hartford National News”, 1966 (Box 35)
      - Photographs of Hartford, 1960s
    - Memorabilia
      - Honor Roll plaque (Oversize), undated
      - Seals (2), undated
  - Subseries D: Hartford National Corporation, 1969-1988
    - Financial Records
      - Cash book, 1971-1972 (Box 36)
      - Shipping documents, 1971-1973
      - Purchase orders, 1971-1975
    - Corporate Records
      - Annual Reports, 1969-1986 (Box 37)
      - Mergers and consolidations, 1981-1987
    - Customer Records
      - Correspondence, 1969-1975 (Box 38)
    - Advertisements and Promotional Publications
      - Articles about merger with Connecticut National Bank, 1981-1983 (Box 39)
      - “Omnihousing”, undated (Box 40)
    - Memorabilia
      - Paper weight of Annual Report, 1979 (Box 41)
      - Paper weight of Report to Stockholders, 1986
      - Paper weight of Prospects Settlement, 1993
      - Item from teller cage, undated
      - Gavel, undated
      - Books about banking, [1926-1977] (Box 42)
      - Books about Hartford, [1933-1972] (Box 43)
  - Subseries E: Shawmut National Corporation, undated, 1892-1995
    - Corporate Records
      - Stock ledger, 1892-1945 (Box 44)
      - Annual Reports, 1985-1994
      - Mergers and consolidations, 1987-1995
    - Memorabilia
      - Coin bank, undated
      - Paper weight of Report of Stocks, undated
      - Seals (4), undated
- Series II: Connecticut National Bank, 1806-1982
  - Subseries A: Bridgeport (National) Bank, 1806-1908
    - Corporate Records
      - Stock ledger, 1835-1877 (Box 45)
      - Stock transfer book, 1865-1906 (Box 46)
      - Stock ledger, 1807-1833 (Box 47)
      - Stock certificates, 1807-1848
      - Stockholders and directors meetings, 1850-1909 (Box 48)
      - Stock certificates, 1865-1900 (Box 49)
      - Founding of Bridgeport National Bank, 1806
      - Mergers and consolidations, 1909
    - Customer Records
      - Checks and checkbooks, 1807-1908
      - Correspondence, 1906
    - Advertisements and Promotional Publications
      - Photograph of bank interior, 1901 (?)
  - Subseries B: First Bridgeport National Bank, 1909-1921
    - Corporate Records
      - Director's meeting book, 1909-1916 (Box 50)
      - Board of Directors minutes, 1917-1921 (Box 51)
      - Certificate: Federal Reserve Bank, 1919
      - Mergers and consolidations, 1913-1921
      - Special meeting of directors, 1919
      - Stock certificate, 1913
      - Board of Directors meetings, 1914-1921 (Box 52)
    - Customer Records
      - Checks, 1909-1915
      - Correspondence, 1921
    - Condensed Statements of Condition, 1907-1920 (Box 53)
    - Reports of Condition, 1908-1919 (Box 54)
  - Subseries C: First National Bank of Bridgeport, 1921-1929
    - Corporate Records
      - Executive Committee minute book, 1921-1924 (Box 55)
      - Board of Directors minutes, 1922-1929 (Box 56)
      - Stock Certificates, 1923
    - Customer Records
      - Correspondence, 1923 (Box 57)
    - Reports of Condition, 1920-1933 (Box 58)
    - Condensed Statements of Condition, 1921-1929
    - Advertisement and Promotional Publications
      - “Bridgeport Life”, 1928
  - Subseries D: First National Bank and Trust Company of Bridgeport, 1929-1955
    - Financial Records
      - Tax Returns, 1935-1958 (Box 59-60)
    - Corporate Records
      - Board of Directors minutes, 1930-1948 (Box 61)
      - Board of Directors minutes, 1949-1954 (Box 62)
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1933-1954
      - Bank examination, 1938 (Box 63)
      - Reports to Mr. Lewis Shea (President), 1936
      - Employee Records, 1947-1955
      - Director's examination committee, 1944 (Box 64)
      - Executive Committee reports, 1939-1940 (Box 65-67)
      - Executive Committee reports, 1949-1950 (Box 68)
      - Executive Committee meetings, 1925-1933 (Box 69)
      - Certificates, 1929-1952
      - Mergers and consolidations, 1950
    - Customer Records
      - Check Stubs, 1929-1932 (Box 70)
    - Loan Records
      - Resume covering loans, 1937
    - Reports of Condition, 1931-1954 (Box 71-72)
    - Condensed Statements of Condition, 1929-1954 (Box 73)
  - Subseries E: Connecticut National Bank, 1955-1982
    - Corporate Records
      - Board of Directors Minutes, 1955-1967 (Box 74)
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1955-1967 (Box 75)
      - Board of Directors minutes, 1968-1970 (Box 76)
      - Executive Committee minutes, 1968-1971
      - Mergers and Consolidations, 1955-1971
      - Reports on Examination, 1955-1956
      - Reports on Examination, 1957-1961 (Box 77)
      - Reports on Examination, 1962-1967 (Box 78)
      - Annual Reports, 1954-1981 (Box 79)
      - Shareholders minutes, 1955-1970 (Box 80)
      - Economic briefs, 1965
      - Economic briefs, 1968
      - Economic briefs, 1969
    - Executive Committee Reports (ECR) and Board of Directors Reports (BDR)
      - ECR & BDR, 1956-1957 (Box 82)
      - ECR & BDR, 1956-1957 (Box 83)
      - ECR, 1957 (Box 84)
      - BDR, 1957-1958 (Box 85)
      - ECR, 1957-1960 (Box 86)
      - ECR, 1960 (Box 87)
      - ECR & BDR, 1959-1961 (Box 88)
      - ECR & BDR, 1961-1962 (Box 89)
      - ECR & BDR, 1962 (Box 90)
      - BDR, 1962-1963 (Box 91)
      - ECR & BDR, 1963 (Box 92)
      - ECR & BDR, 1963 (Box 93)
      - ECR & BDR, 1964 (Box 94)
      - ECR & BDR, 1964-1965 (Box 95)
      - ECR & BDR, 1965 (Box 96)
      - ECR & BDR, 1966 (Box 97)
      - ECR & BDR, 1966 (Box 98)
      - ECR & BDR, 1967 (Box 99)
      - ECR & BDR, 1968 (Box 100)
      - ECR & BDR, 1968 (Box 101)
      - ECR & BDR, 1968 (Box 102)
      - ECR & BDR, 1969 (Box 103)
      - ECR & BDR, 1969 (Box 104)
      - ECR & BDR, 1970 (Box 105)
      - ECR & BDR, 1970 (Box 106)
      - ECR & BDR, 1971 (Box 107)
      - ECR & BDR, 1971 (Box 108)
      - ECR & BDR, 1972 (Box 109)
      - ECR & BDR, 1972 (Box 110)
    - Reports of Condition, 1955-1970 (Box 111)
    - Condensed Statements of Condition, 1955-1974 (Box 112)
    - "History of Connecticut", undated (Box 113)
    - Advertisements and Promotional Publications
      - Photographs of bank and personnel, 1950s (Box 114)
      - Subject files, 1950s (Box 114)
      - 150th Anniversary, 1956
      - History of the Connecticut National Bank, 1956
- Series III: Merger Banks, undated, 1792-1988
  - Subseries A: Hartford National Corporation, 1792-1988
    - Aetna National Bank, 1857-1915
      - Aetna National Bank of Hartford, 1907 (Box 115)
    - Bankers Trust Company, 1924-1933
      - Loan records, 1929-1940
      - Loan records, 1933-1934
      - Loan records, 1931-1934
      - Report on examination, 1932
      - Reports of condition, 1933 (Box 116)
      - Tax returns, 1927-1933
    - Central National Bank of Middletown, 1865-1955
      - Reports of condition, 1949-1955 (Box 117)
      - Tax returns, 1917-1955
      - Stock ledger, 1865-1915 (Box 118)
      - Director's records, 1919 (Box 119)
      - Director's records, 1926-1934
      - Director's records, 1943-1949
      - Director's records, 1949-1953
      - Director's records, 1954-1955
      - Discount Committee minutes, 1947-1954
    - Chester Trust Company, 1914-1942
      - Stock certificates, 1914-1942 (Box 120)
    - Connecticut River Banking Company, 1824-1954
      - Stock certificates, undated (Box 121)
      - Stock certificates, 1877-1910
      - Stock certificates, 1941-1954
      - Stock transfer book, 1830-1859
      - Stock transfer books, 1904-1944 (Box 122)
      - Stock transfer book, 1946-1954
      - Currency plate, 1852
      - Currency plate, 1865
      - Currency plate, undated
      - Currency plate, undated
      - Currency plate, undated
      - Annual report, 1876 (Box 123)
      - Charter and amendments, 1825-1858
      - Photographs of bank and Hartford, 1800s
      - Post Cards, 1906-1908
      - Reports of condition, 1922-1925
      - Connecticut River Banking Company: One Hundred Years, 1925 (Box 124)
      - Daily balances no. 7, 1882-1885 (Box 125)
      - Account book, 1926-1927 (Volume Vol. 10)
    - East Hartford Trust Company, ?-1950
      - Condensed statement of condition, 1930 (Box 126)
      - “East Hartford Trust Company”, undated
      - Newspaper article, 1924
      - Newspaper article, 1980
      - Stock certificates, 1948-1950
    - Fidelity Trust Company, 1885-1923
      - Board minutes, 1909-1919; (2 vol.) (Box 127)
      - Board minutes, 1923-1941; (4 vol.)
      - Board minutes, 1941-1948; (2 vol.) (Box 128)
      - Board minutes, 1951-1967; (5 vol.)
      - Reports of examination, 192719-40
      - Report of condition, 1921 (Box 129)
      - Stock certificates, 1896-1907